Nadezhda Teodorovich Papers, Inclusive: 1950-1979, undated, Bulk: 1960-1978
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Nadezhda Teodorovich Papers
Inclusive: 1950-1979, undated, Bulk: 1960-1978
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
13
Teodorovich, Nadezhda, 1907 - 1979
83 document boxes
The Nadezhda Teodorovich Papers contain materials produced or collected by Nadezhda Teodorovich, head of the Institute for the Study of the USSR in Munich, Germany.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Nadezhda Aleksandrovna Teodorovich (nee Abramova) (1907 — 1979) was born in 1907 in Belorussia. She attended Minsk Pedagogical University and graduated from Belorussian Medical University. During the German occupation in 1942, Teodorovich founded the Union of Belorussian Youth. The following year, the Nazi government legalized the organization. In 1944, Teodorovich moved to Munich where she lived until her death in 1979.
Teodorovich converted from Eastern Orthodox to Catholic after she emigrated, becoming a member of St. Nicholas Russian Catholic Church of Byzantine Rite in Munich. From 1951 to 1972, she worked as a researcher for the Institute for the Study of the USSR and published the journal “Religion and Atheism in the USSR.” Radio Liberty also employed Dr. Teodorovich who was known for her nationalistic and anti-communist views.
Scope and Content
The Nadezhda Teodorovich Papers consist of research papers, manuscripts, correspondence, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings, church and secular publications, reports on issues of religion and atheism and religious dissidents in the USSR, and the Institute for the Study of the USSR records.
Arrangement
Most of the Nadezhda Teodorovich Papers were received in her original binders organized by topic. However, some papers were also included with other Keston materials. The collection is organized by original binder topics in one series: I. Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 13.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Chalidze, Valeri, 1938-; Levitin-Krasnov, A. (Anatoli mmanuilovich), 1915-1991.; Orlov, IUri Fedorovich.; Slipy, Iosyf, 1892-1984.; Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1918-2008.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Byzantine rite, Ukrainian -- Bishops -- Biography.; Catholic Church -- Byzantine rite, Ukrainian.; Institut zur Erforschung der UdSSR.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Obshchestvennaia gruppa sodestviia vypolneniiu Khelsinkskikh soglasheni v SSSR.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov. Moskovskaia patriarkhiia.
Subjects
Antisemitism -- Soviet Union.; Atheism -- Soviet Union.; Church and state -- Soviet Union.; Dissenters -- Soviet Union.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Human rights -- Soviet Union.; Islam -- Soviet Union.; Jews -- Persecutions -- Soviet Union.; Minorities -- Soviet Union.; Muslims -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.; Political prisoners -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Samizdat.
- Subject Files, 1950-1979, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  - Levitin-Krasnov, Anatolii (1 of 2), 1965-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Levitin-Krasnov, Anatolii (2 of 2), 1964-1971, 1974, 1975, undated (Box 2)
  - Baptists (1 of 2), 1964-1970 (Box 3)
  - Baptists (2 of 2), 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Biography. Ukraine. Catholics, 1957, undated (Box 5)
  - Religious Radio Programs, 1968-1969, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Buddhism in the USSR, 1955, 1963, 1966, 1971-1975 (Box 7)
  - Buddhism in Tibet and India, 1959 (Box 8)
  - Catholic Church (1 of 2), 1957, undated (Box 9)
  - Catholic Church (2 of 2), 1961, undated (Box 10)
  - Christian Sectarianism (1 of 2), 1958 - 1965 (Box 11)
  - Christian Sectarianism (2 of 2), 1958 - 1965 (Box 12)
  - Dissidents in Emigration, 1965-1975, undated (Box 13)
  - G-K (1 of 2), 1974-1977 (Box 14)
  - G-K (2 of 2), 1974-1977 (Box 15)
  - Helsinki Conference Materials, Reports, 1976-1978, undated (Box 16)
  - Human Rights (1 of 2), 1968-1977 (Box 17)
  - Human Rights (2 of 2), 1968-1977 (Box 18)
  - Human Rights in the USSR, 1977 - 1978 (Box 19)
  - Islam, 1953, 1961-1978, undated (Box 20)
  - Islam 1 (1 of 2), 1954, 1961, undated (Box 21)
  - Islam 1 (2 of 2), 1955-1967, undated (Box 22)
  - Islam 2 (1 of 2), 1957-1968, 1970, undated (Box 23)
  - Islam 2 (2 of 2), 1955-1959, undated (Box 24)
  - Jews (1 of 2), 1963-1977, undated (Box 25)
  - Jews (2 of 2), 1968 - 1971 (Box 26)
  - Letters. List of German Samizdat, 1974-1976, undated (Box 27)
  - Materials and Reports, Institute for Study of the USSR (1 of 2), 1959 — 1964 (Box 28)
  - Materials and Reports, Institute for Study of the USSR (2 of 2), 1959 — 1964 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous: Articles, Appeals, Letters. SAMIZDAT Materials on ROC in the USSR, 1922-1977, undated (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (German, Russian), List of Sources, Contributors, and Participants (1 of 2), 1917-1976, undated (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (German, Russian), List of Sources, Contributors, and Participants (2 of 2), 1944-1987, undated (Box 32)
  - Teodorovich, Nadezhda, “Episcopate of the ROC — Victim of the Communist Terror”, 1913-1991, undated (Box 33)
  - Teodorovich, Nadezhda, "Episcopate of the Russian Orthodox Church - Victim of the Communist Terror" (Carbon Copies), 1917-1980, undated (Box 34)
  - Personal and Group Initiatives (1 of 2), 1956-1975, undated (Box 35)
  - Personal and Group Initiatives (2 of 2), 1966-1975, undated (Box 36)
  - Prisoners. Names and Addresses, 1941-1978, undated (Box 37)
  - Psychiatric Hospitals in the USSR (1 of 3), 1970-1977 (Box 38)
  - Psychiatric Hospitals in the USSR (2 of 3), 1970-1977 (Box 39)
  - Psychiatric Hospitals in the USSR (3 of 3), 1970-1977 (Box 40)
  - Literature and Miscellaneous Materials (January 1975). World Council of Churches (Kenya, USSR), 1945-1981, undated (Box 41)
  - Signs of Violence (Extracts) (1 of 2), 1965-1975, undated (Box 42)
  - Signs of Violence (Extracts) (2 of 2), 1967-1975 (Box 43)
  - Solzhenitsyn (1 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 44)
  - Solzhenitsyn (2 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 45)
  - Solzhenitsyn (3 of 4), 1974-1978 (Box 46)
  - Solzhenitsyn (4 of 4), 1974-1978 (Box 47)
  - Soviet Dissidents (1 of 2), 1969 - 1978 (Box 48)
  - Soviet Dissidents (2 of 2), 1969 - 1978 (Box 49)
  - Typescripts (1 of 6), 1954-1963, undated (Box 50)
  - Typescripts (2 of 6), 1917-1962, undated (Box 51)
  - Typescripts (3 of 6), 1912-1975, undated (Box 52)
  - Typescripts (4 of 6), 1927-1964, undated (Box 53)
  - Typescripts (5 of 6), 1929-1962, undated (Box 54)
  - Typescripts (6 of 6), 1914-1977, undated (Box 55)
  - V. Chalidze, 1967-1972 (Box 56)
  - Biographies, 1923-1971, undated (Box 57)
  - Bishops, 1953-1973 (Box 58)
  - Conference "Religion and Atheism." Personal Correspondence, 1965-1978, undated (Box 59)
  - Foreign Correspondence. European Affairs. Human Rights, 1965-1979, undated (Box 60)
  - Correspondence with Foreign Media, Governments, 1965-1978, undated (Box 61)
  - Helsinki Group, 1973-1978, undated (Box 62)
  - Legislative Terror (1 of 2), 1959-1978 (Box 63)
  - Legislative Terror (2 of 2), 1945-1975, undated (Box 64)
  - Crimean Tatars (1 of 2), 1968 - 1971 (Box 65)
  - Crimean Tatars (2 of 2), 1972 - 1978 (Box 66)
  - Ukrainian Samizdat Materials (1 of 2), 1967-1983, undated (Box 67)
  - Ukrainian Samizdat Materials (2 of 2), 1967-1977 (Box 68)
  - Soviet Institute for the Study of History and Culture (Africa, Germany, Belorussia, Ukraine, Baltics, Caucasus, Middle East, Central Asian Republics), 1958-1966, undated (Box 69)
  - Political and Religious Prisoners in the USSR: Trials, Sentences, and Detention Conditions (1 of 2), 1969-1977 (Box 70)
  - Political and Religious Prisoners in the USSR: Trials, Sentences, and Detention Conditions ( 2 of 2), 1966-1977 (Box 71)
  - Miscellaneous: WCC and the USSR, Statistics, Contacts for "Religion and Atheism", Materials in German, 1958-1978, undated (Box 72)
  - Iurii Orlov Trial, 1978 (Box 73)
  - Moscow Patriarchate, 1967-1971 (Box 74)
  - Moscow Patriarchate Since Patriarch Pimen, 1972 (Box 75)
  - Samizdat Materials, 1970-1972 (Box 76)
  - Samizdat Materials: Memorandums, 1969 July-1970 March (Box 77)
  - Samizdat Materials: Jews in the USSR, 1967-1976, undated (Box 78)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959 - 1968 (Box 79)
  - Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia (1 of 2), 1947, 1958, 1963-1976, undated (Box 80)
  - Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia (2 of 2), 1951-1978, undated (Box 81)
  - Publications. Articles, 1969 - 1975 (Box 82)
  - Publications: Novels. Poems. Magazines, 1968 - 1976 (Box 83)